

YOHAN GRENIER

DATA ANALYST



74100 VETRAZ-MONTHOUX



VEHICLE LICENCES A & B WORK PERMIT G

AGE 30



YGDATA.CH



Y.GRENIER@PROTONMAIL.COM



+33 648 648 916



IMMEDIATELY AVAILABLE

PROFILE

With 9 years' experience, I'm constantly evolving and have recently consolidated my IT skills and enhanced my analytical expertise. I'm actively seeking a stimulating environment where I can use my strengths to make a significant contribution to the success of your company. My strong commitment to excellence makes me the ideal candidate for the challenges ahead. Let's talk about it!

QUALIFICATIONS

2023 - ENSAE Paris & OPENCLASSROOM Data Analyst (Master I - RNCP 6)

2022 - European certification

ECDL Excel Advanced

2021 - VAF

N S

Α

Ε

& 0

Ρ

CFC Retail manager

2011 - High School Diploma Industrial Science & Technology

SKILLS

ABILITY TO ANALYSE AND SYNTHESISE SCIENTIFIC RIGOUR BUSINESS AND MARKETING CULTURE CREATIVITY FLEXIBILITY AND RESPONSIVENESS **GOOD SOCIAL SKILLS** PEDAGOGICAL DISCRETION IT & DIGITAL LECTURER

KNOWLEDGE

PYTHON MACHINE LEARNING STATISTICS **EXCEL** VBA SOL POWERPOINT POWER BI MICROSOFT 365 SAP **ENGLISH - B2 LEVEL** FRENCH - NATIVE LANGUAGE

EXPERIENCES

DATA ANALYST

Tools used: Python, Excel, PowerBi, DAX, UML, SQL, Knime, Powerpoint

• DEVELOP AN AUTOMATED MODEL TO DETECT COUNTERFEIT BANKNOTES:

Exploratory data analysis, imputation of missing values by linear regression and construction of a detection model (models tested: Logistic Regression, KNN and Kmeans) then evaluation and optimisation of its performance Technologies used: Python [Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-learn, Scipy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly]

ANALYSIS FOR INTERNATIONAL EXPORT :

Collection of data from different sources to meet PESTEL analysis criteria to identify clusters of countries to target by reducing dimensions (PCA) and using algorithms (Kmeans & AHC)

Technologies used: Python [Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-learn, Scipy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly], Excel, PowerPoint

RESPONDING TO A NEED TO MONITOR MOTORCYCLIST ACCIDENTS IN SWITZERLAND FOR THE OFROU:

After a blueprint, a mock-up and the review of current and passed papers, data was collected from various public sources, then the database was mapped on PowerBi in order to create dynamic reports at different granularities

Technologies used: PowerBi, PowerQuery, DAX, Excel, Powerpoint

• COMPLETE ANALYSIS FOR STRATEGIC DECISION-MAKING:

Using time series, statistical tests and R.F.M. segmentation, definition of proposed offers, price adjustments and target

Technologies used: Python [Pandas, NumPy, Statsmodels, Scipy, Matplotlib, Seaborn], Excel, PowerPoint, Shorthand

• IN-DEPTH STUDY ON GLOBAL UNDERNUTRITION FOR THE UNITED NATIONS (FAO) :

After the state of the art and the collection of public data, investigation of the current and passed papers of the problem and its causes, considering all related issues (political stability, war, GDP, road infrastructure, etc.)

Technologies used: Python [Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn], Excel, PowerPoint

• STRATEGIC PROJECT TO CREATE A PREDICTIVE MODEL FOR PROPERTY PRICES :

Modification and modelling of the database by incorporating information extracted from public data, then querying to obtain initial indicators

Technologies used: SQL, SQLite, UML, Excel

E N c L A S R 0 WITH 0 М

CONCRETE **PROJECTS** SUBMITTED 2023 - 2024

R S

S

P A

MMM BALEXERT

COOPERATIVE

MIGROS

2021 - 2023

9

COOPERATIVE MIGROS 2014 - 2021

SPORTXX

MARKET MANAGEMENT SUPPORT COORDINATOR & SALES

Tools used: Excel, VBA, Powerpoint, Sharepoint, Planner, PowerBi, Python, SAP

• ANALYSES AND SYNTHESES OF KPIS WITH A TURNOVER OF AROUND 100M CHF/YEAR:

Synthesise the situation of KPIs & benchmarks in order to highlight useful insights for the management team, the Steering Committee or the Executive Committee

Technologies used: Excel, Python [NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn]

• PRESENTATION OF RESULTS AND SUGGESTED APPLICATIONS TO OPTIMISE KPI:

Weekly summary session on the status of the KPIs for the 12 managers, the deputy and the managing director Technologies used: Powerpoint, PowerBi

• TRAINING AND MANAGEMENT OF IT TOOLS FOR A TEAM OF 180 PEOPLE :

Documenting operations and procedures, and training next to monitoring operational colleagues Technologies used: Powerpoint

• IMPLEMENTATION OF PILOT PROJECTS, SHARING PLATFORMS AND PROCEDURES :

Making news available to everyone by creating Sharepoint pages and organising tasks using Planner Technologies used : Sharepoint, Planner

• SIMPLIFYING THE DAY-TO-DAY WORK OF OPERATIONAL STAFF AND IMPROVING EFFICIENCY:

Automate recurring tasks by transforming 3 hours/week of research into ONE click using VBA Technologies used: Excel, VBA

• MANAGEMENT OF GOODS MOVEMENTS, CONTRACTS AND B2B|B2C ORDERS:

Organise and control the various indicators, then communicate solutions to the right persons Technologies used : SAP, Excel, Planner

SALESPERSON | SECOND SHOP MANAGER

Tools used: Excel, Powerpoint, SAP

• SALES ANALYSIS:

Search for increases in sales performance according to position, season and various KPIs

 $\label{tensor} \mbox{Technologies used}: \mbox{ Excel, SAP}$

• PRO-ACTIVE SEARCH FOR IMPROVEMENTS :

By monitoring trend / the competition and looking for new partners $% \left(1\right) =\left(1\right) \left(1\right)$

Sources used : Google Trend, réseaux sociaux, clientèle

• B2C CONTRACT MANAGEMENT :

Creation of contracts for customers either internally or directly with suppliers

Technologies used: Excel, SAP

• CONFLICT MANAGEMENT:

Adapting my language and finding a solution for the customer without affecting the organisation

• TEAM MANAGEMENT :

Managing a team of 11 people and relaying with the $n+^{1}$ - 2 hierarchy and the merchandiser

PERSONALITY

I have an optimistic temperament, I'm also dynamic and constantly cheerful. My self-control and ability to adapt are admired by those close to me. These qualities stem from my incessant curiosity, which leads me to see problems as challenges to be met, convinced that there is always a solution. It encourages me to think 'out of the box' and to dedicate free time to platforms such as CodinGame.

Having recently consolidated my statistical and algorithmic approach, I'm looking forward to applying and sharing my knowledge on high-impact, high-stakes assignments where my interest in programming and the search for insights can be exploited to the maximum.



Hiking - Skiing

IT - IT News



Bouldering - Freediving



Travel - Motorcycles



DIY